Did you know that the Giza pyramid Khufu is made up of two million blocks?
هل تعلم أن هرم "خوفو" في "الجيزة" مبني من مليوني لبنة؟
Well, imagine we want to build our own small pyramid here that looks something like this.
حسناً، تخيل أننا نريد بناء هرم صغير هنا يبدو هكذا تقريباً.
The lowest layer is made up of nine blocks, three times three.
أدنى طبقة مبنية من تسع لبنات، 3 ضرب 3.
And then the second layer is made up of a two by two grid block,
ثم تتشكل الطبقة الثانية من شبكة 2 ضرب 2.
and then the last layer is just this one block.
والطبقة الأخيرة تتشكل من لبنة واحدة فقط.
This pyramid is made up of 14 blocks.
يتكون هذا الهرم من 14 لبنة.
One plus four plus nine.
1 زائد 4 زائد 9.
Now think, what if we wanted to add another layer
فكر الآن، ماذا لو أردنا إضافة طبقة أخرى
underneath that's made up of five by five blocks?
في الأسفل تتكون من شبكة بأبعاد5 ضرب 5؟
How many total number of blocks would we need to build that pyramid?
ما مجموع اللبنات الذي سنحتاجه لبناء ذلك الهرم؟
What if we wanted our pyramid to be 100 levels high?
ماذا لو أردنا أن يكون هرمنا بعلو 100 طبقة؟
Well, the number of blocks grows really quickly.
حسناً، عدد اللبنات يتزايد بسرعة،
So, instead of having to count the number of blocks manually,
لذا، بدلاً من حساب عدد اللبنات بطريقة يدوية،
why don't you write a Java function that would
لما لا نكتب دالة Java
calculate the total number of blocks for you?
تقوم بحساب مجموع اللبنات من أجلك؟
It can take an input argument,
يمكنها تقبل وسيطة ادخال
that is the number of levels that we want,
تمثل عدد الطبقات التي نريدها،
and it will return the number of blocks required to build the pyramid.
وستنتج عدد اللبنات المطلوبة لبناء الهرم.
For example, in this case here,
ففي هذه الحالة مثلاً،
if it takes the input three,
إذا قبلت المدخل 3،
then it will return 14 because we need three times three,
فستنتج 14 لأننا نحتاج إلى 3 ضرب 3
plus two times two,
زائد 2 ضرب 2
plus one, which is 14.
زائد 1، وهذه تساوي 14.
So, instead of having to count the blocks manually,
لذا بدلاً من الحاجة لعد اللبنات يدوياً،
why don't you write a Java function that would
لماذا لا تكتب دالة Java
calculate the total number of blocks for you?
تحسب مجموع اللبنات من أجلك؟
It would take an input, which is equal to the number of levels in that pyramid,
ستقبل مدخلاً يساوي عدد الطبقات في ذلك الهرم،
and it would output the number of blocks needed to build such pyramid.
وستنتج عدد اللبنات المطلوبة لبناء مثل ذلك الهرم.
In this case for example,
في هذه الحالة مثلاً،
the input would be equal to three,
سيكون المدخل 3،
and it would calculate the number of blocks to be 14.
وستحسب عدد اللبنات ليكون 14.
The way it works is it adds the number of blocks for
طريقة عملها هي أنها تضيف عدد اللبنات في كل طبقة
each level starting with the first one, one times one,
ابتداءً بالطبقة الأولى، 1 ضرب 1،
plus the second layer,
زائد الطبقة الثانية
which is formed of two times two blocks,
المكونة من لبنات بعدد 2 ضرب 2.
plus the third layer, which is made up of three times three blocks.
زائد الطبقة الثالثة المكونة من لبنات بعدد 3 ضرب 3.
Adding those numbers together gives us the value of 14,
إضافة هذه الأعداد إلى بعضها سيعطينا قيمة 14،
which is the output of this function.
وهي المخرج لهذه الدالة.
Try to implement this function so that it works with any input we give it,
حاول تطبيق هذه الدالة لتعمل مع أي مدخل نعطيها،
and it would calculate the number of blocks for such pyramid.
وتحسب عدد اللبنات لمثل هذا الهرم.